Vodou religious expression in Haiti collected by Odette Mennesson Rigaud, Milo Rigaud, and Shirley Keller
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
- Series 2: Vodou-related recordings
  - Sound recording, undated, AFC 2019/041: SR035; RYE 8034; 1 sound cassette (Side A: 00:32:30, Side B: 00:29:10): analog, 1 7/8 ips, half track, mono
    Side B: The content begins at 00:00:09. This side seems to be a continuation from Side A, with a man singing to stringed instrument accompaniment, with at least one extended solo on the instrument. Instruments played include a stringed instrument (possibly a guitar) and drums.
    Written on the cassette housing: IIA #6 / Voodoo [sic] ceremonies recorded on wire by Odette Rigaud / put onto digital master - made by Bob Avedon - Park Ridge, N.J.
  - Sound recording, undated, AFC 2019/041: SR036; RAA 66287; 1 sound tape reel (polyester, 00:11:00): analog, 7 1/2 ips; half-track, stereo and mono; 10 in.; This tape was received without an individual tape box.
    Shirley Keller records herself speaking into a tape recorder, and uses another recorder to play back music performances and parts of Vodou ceremonies. She talks about Haitian drumming and her first experience attending a Vodou ceremony, in 1975. She mentions Diane (probably Diane Wolkstein) and Marie (otherwise unidentified). At 00:06:56 she mentions Milo Rigaud.
    Written on the tape reel flange: Voodoo [sic]
  - Sound recording, undated, AFC 2019/041: SR037; RYF 1129; 1 sound cassette (Side A: 00:42:00, Side B: 00:45:34): analog, 1 7/8 ips, half track, mono
    Side A: The content begins about 00:00:13. People are speaking while instruments are being played. For more than one song, a man leads the singing for a chorus of mixed voices. A dog can be heard barking. There are instances of hand clapping. The recording ends abruptly. Instruments played include drums, metal percussion, and rattles.
    Side B: The content begins about 00:00:20. One man and sometimes two men lead a group of mixed voices in song, accompanied by rattles and drums. At one point a chicken can be heard clucking. The recording ends abruptly. Instruments played include drums, rattles, and metal percussion.
    Transcription:
    Box panel: Side A: I #3 / Side B: #4 #5
  - Sound recording, undated, AFC 2019/041: SR038; RYF 8606; 1 sound cassette (Side A: 00:32:30, Side B: 00:18:00): analog, 1 7/8 ips, half track, mono; SR038, SR039, and SR040 have identical content.
    Side A: The content begins about 00:00:15. Vocal performances. Musical instruments include drums and metal percussion. The recording ends abruptly.
    Side B: The content begins about 00:00:05. Mixed voices, sometimes with a leader, perform songs. Conversations can be heard. Musical instruments include drums, rattles and other percussion, and whistles. The recording ends abruptly.
    Box panel: Side A: III #7 / Side B: #7, continued
  - Sound recording, undated, AFC 2019/041: SR039; RYH 8997; 1 sound cassette (Side A: 00:32:31, Side B: 00:18:00): analog, 1 7/8 ips, half track, mono; SR038, SR039, and SR040 have identical content.
  - Sound recording, undated, AFC 2019/041: SR040; RYL 4397; 1 sound cassette (Side A: 00:32:36, Side B: 00:18:00): analog, 1 7/8 ips, half track, mono; SR038, SR039, and SR040 have identical content.
  - Sound recording, undated, AFC 2019/041: SR041; RYL 4476; 1 sound cassette (Side A: 00:47:00, Side B: 00:41:40): analog, 1 7/8 ips, half track, mono
    Side A: The content begins about 00:00:23. Mixed voices, sometimes with a leader, perform songs. Hand clapping can be heard. At 00:33:19 a woman says "chants des travailleurs" (worker's songs); this may be Marie Rigaud. At 00:41:34 a horn honks twice (possibly a car passing by). The recording ends abruptly. Musical instruments include drums, metal percussion, and rattles.
    Side B: The content begins about 00:00:06. Mixed voices, sometimes with a leader, perform songs. Hand clapping can be heard. There are occasional, brief conversations. The recording ends abruptly. Musical instruments include drums, rattles, and metal percussion
    Written on the cassette housing: 100 / [Side] B
  - Sound recording, undated, AFC 2019/041: SR042; RYL 9619; 1 sound cassette (00:30:30): analog, 1 7/8 ips, half track, mono
    Content begins about 00:00:08. The first two songs are sung by two different men, possibly with one woman singing in the background. The balance of the recording has mixed voices, sometimes with a leader, who perform songs. From about 00:10:48-00:12:17 a woman sings solo and a cappella. Conversations can be heard. Audio distortion from the source recording towards the end of the tape. The recording ends abruptly. Musical instruments played include drums, rattles, metal percussion, and whistles.
    Written on the cassette housing: Voodoo [sic] - Rigaud tape - #? [sic]
  - Sound recording, April 21, 1972, AFC 2019/041: SR044; RXK 4061; 1 sound reel (acetate, 00:55:00): analog, 3 3/4 ips, full track mono; 7 in.; Aircheck date: April 21, 1972.; The recording has commercial breaks, editorials, and other parts of the recording unrelated to the interview from about 00:00:05-00:05:10, 00:11:50-00:15:10, 00:24:24-00:31:41, 00:41:52-00:43:45, and 00:52:03-00:55:00 (end).
    Bruce Lee interviews Odette Rigaud about various topics related to Vodou. She talks about her association with Vodou, Vodou as a religion and not black magic, her interest in African sculpture and religion, the exhibit of her photographs at the Elma Lewis Center, Vodou in Haiti, the perception of Vodou as black magic, the role of missionaries in developing this perception, Haiti as a colony and the perception of colonists about Vodou, elements of Christianity in Vodou, lwa (spirits) as emanations from God. Rudy Robinson (a professional photographer) and Barry Gaither are introduced. Barry's connection with the Elma Lewis Center exhibition was to work with Odette Rigaud for two weeks to select images for the show, and the time and effort involved in discussions and the selection process. Barry Gaither, the director of the art teaching program at the center, and is also the curator and director for the museum program of the National Center of Afro-American Artists (which includes the Elma Lewis School of Fine Arts) talks about "Ah-Haiti: Glimpses of Voodoo [sic] " (the exhibit's title) and the focus on Vodou as a series topic, details about the exhibit, plans for a traveling exhibit, publication of the book Secrets of Vodou in English, and access to the center. The guests respond to questions called in by listeners. Part 1 effectively ends at 00:52:03.
    The show spans three recordings in the collection (regardless of the documentation that accompanies the tapes); this is part 1. See SR046 for part 2 and SR045 for part 3. See SR047 for a dub of part 1.
    Box panel: Rigaud / Bay St Forum / 1
    Information from the donor (written on the tape box): 12 / 12-1 Boston, Mass. Radio station WEEI Interview of Odette M. Rigaud on the Bruce Lee Show. 1 Hour - 3 3/4 speed / transferred to cassette #12 by Shirley Keller 5-9-82
  - Sound recording, April 21, 1972, AFC 2019/041: SR046; RXK 4063; 1 sound reel (acetate, 00:59:46): analog, 3 3/4 ips, full track mono; 7 in.; The date noted is the aircheck date.; The recording has commercial breaks, news reports, and other parts of the recording unrelated to the interview from about 00:00:06-00:05:14, 00:12:10-00:13:23, 00:17:07-00:19:52, 00:24:21-00:25:02, 00:29:11-00:30:16, 00:30:53-00:33:43, 00:33:56-00:35:00, 00:43:29-00:44:01 00:56:01-00:59:46 (end). The tape has audio gaps at 00:29:06 and at 00:44:01, as if it has been edited to exclude content. This tape may be a dub copy of the original recording.
    Continuation of the Bruce Lee show, beginning at 00:05:15. A story is continued, regarding a young Puerto Rican girl who traveled to Haiti and was healed by lwa. The panel discusses the nature of healing and the role of lwa, and discuss lwa with a man who call in to the show. Rigaud explains the how the word "Vodou" is used in Haiti (the name of the religion and also as an adjective). A woman calls the show and asks Rigaud about a particular ceremony she witnessed in Haiti, and asked Rigaud to explain the ceremony. Rigaud suggested that she may have witnessed a ceremony presented for the benefit of tourists. Another caller asks for guidance if someone is using Vodou to gain control over her. Rigaud recommends she pray to her own deity for protection. She responds to a caller who asks about elements of Vodou practice that he has observed. Barry Gaither gives an overview of the exhibit at the Elma Lewis Center. The panel discusses the perception of Vodou in America. They talk with a caller concerned about her teenage son; it turns out there was no relationship between her inquiry and Vodou. The recording ends abruptly.
    See SR044 for part 1 of the show and SR045 for part 3.
    Box panel: Interview with Odette Rigaud by Bruce Lee - 1972 WEEI. I think this should be played after tape 12 and 13 is played after this for connect [?] [?].
    Information from the donor (written on the tape box): 1-2 Re-recorded on to cassette #14 by Shirley Keller - May 1982. Subject, continued from tape 13
  - Sound recording, April 21, 1972, AFC 2019/041: SR045; RXK 4062; 1 sound reel (acetate, 00:27:44): analog, 3 3/4 ips, full track mono; 7 in.; Aircheck date: April 21, 1972.; The recording has commercial breaks, news reports, and other parts of the recording unrelated to the interview from about 00:00:04-00:04:05.
    See SR044 for part 1 of the show and SR046 for part 3. See SR048 for a dub of this recording.
    The interview portion of the recording begins about 00:04:06. Barry Gaither speaks about the center's interest in archival materials, how the current show evolved, and the preparations. Gaither and Robinson talk about how preparations changed them, and Odette Rigaud's impact on them and her personality. Bruce Lee talks about his admiration for the exhibit. Gaither and Robinson talk about the exhibit going on tour, Rigaud's ability as a photographer, and the nature of a visual exhibit. The panel engage in a conversation with a caller. The show effectively ends at 00:27:22. The tape ends abruptly shortly after that.
    Information from the donor (written on the tape box): 13 / Continuation of tape 12 - Radio Interview of Odette Rigaud by Bruce Lee - WEEI. Boston, Mass. Rerecorded by Shirley Keller on cassette #13 on 5-9-82. 2-230
  - Sound recording, undated, AFC 2019/041: SR047; RYN 9461; 1 sound cassette (Side A: 00:28:30, Side B: 00:26:13): analog, 1 7/8, half track, stereo
    SR047 is a dub copy of SR044.
    Written on the cassette housing: 12 - Odette Rigaud - Radio Shoro [?] / WEEI - Boston, Mass. / Bruce Lee - interviewer
  - Sound recording, undated, AFC 2019/041: SR048; RYR 3920; 1 sound cassette (00:27:00): analog, 1 7/8, half track, stereo; Side B is blank. The cassette has been reshelled. Poor audio with many dropouts from the source tape used to make this cassette.
    SR048 is a dub copy of SR045.
    Written on the cassette housing: 13 - Bruce Lee Interviews Odette Rigaud - WEEI - Boston, Mass.
  - Sound recording, undated, AFC 2019/041: SR049; RYR 3921; 1 sound cassette (Side A: 00:28:00, Side B: 00:16:45): analog, 1 7/8, half track, stereo
    Side A: The content begins about 00:00:08. A large group of mixed voices sing more than one song, with a male lead singer. Instruments include drums, metal percussion, whistles, and possibly other instruments.
    Side B: The content begins about 00:00:05. A large group of mixed voices sing more than one song. Frequently, a male singer can be heard above the other singers, possibly leading the song. Instruments include drums, metal percussion, rattles, and possibly other instruments.
    Written on the cassette housing: Milo Rigaud - Voodoo [sic] / #2
  - Sound recording, circa 1980-1981, AFC 2019/041: SR050; RYR 3922; 1 sound cassette (00:23:00): analog, 1 7/8 ips, half track, stereo format, mono audio; This is either a copy of SR050 or the original recording. Side B is blank.
    The content begins about 00:00:05. Shirley Keller interviews Milo Rigaud during his hospital stay. The recording begins with Shirley suggesting he addresses Odette in French (his "native language"). Next, he mentions his younger brother Carl, who lives in his own home in Port-au-Prince. Keller has difficulty understanding what he says. Milo writes down his brother's address, since Keller has offered to contact Carl. She says she can record Milo speaking, and take the cassette to Carl and play it for him. He speaks in French, addressing his brother. He tells Shirley that his brother was in the same hospital last year for surgery. Shirley and Milo talk about his diet (foods he is permitted and enjoys). Milo talks about visitors he has while in the hospital. They make small talk, and then talk about his book, and the difficulties of publishing a book in New York, written in French. They talk about the need for a translator to understand about Vodou to translate the text accurately. He talks about Odette's wish to return to Haiti with him [currently, they are in New York]. The talk about the work of writing a book, and where he and Odette would live when they return to Haiti. They talk further about his brother, and as they say their farewells, they make further small talk. Shirley mentions Diane [probably Diane Wolkstein]. Milo gives Shirley contact information for a person in Haiti [unclear if this is to help her find a house]. The recording ends abruptly.
    Box panel: Haiti - Odette Rigaud - Milo / their voices
    Written on the cassette housing: Side A: Milo to Odette and Karl; Side B: Odette to Michelle
  - Sound recording, undated, AFC 2019/041: SR051; RYR 3923; 1 sound cassette (Side A: 00:22:50, Side B: 00:01:00): analog, 1 7/8 ips, half track, stereo format, mono audio; This is either a copy of SR050 or the original recording.
    Side A: See SR050, Side A for a summary of the contents.
    Side B: An unidentified woman speaks in French. "Madame Shirley " (probably Shirley Keller) is mentioned near the end of the recording, which ends abruptly.
    Written on j-card: [j-card spine] Milo Rigaud - in Hospital / message to Odette and Brother in Haiti (198_) [sic] [Side A] Milo Rigaud / at Hospital / messages to wife Odette and Brother in Haiti - Karl / this made in NYC house [?] / Milo died the day I left for Haiti to see his brother [Side B] Odette Rigaud to Michelle
    Written on the cassette housing: copy only (2012) Milo at Hospital and message to Brother 1981? [sic] / copy - In Hospital Milo sec part on B
  - Sound recording, March 11, 1982, AFC 2019/041: SR052; RYR 3924; 1 sound cassette (00:15:00): analog, 1 7/8 ips, half track, stereo; Side B is blank. Milo and Odette were married in 1935, in New York City. Other details in this recording may need to be cross-checked for accuracy.
    The content begins about 00:00:05. Shirley Keller interviews Odette Rigaud, with a translator present. Shirley asks questions in English, and Odette responds in French, with the translator acting for both. Shirley talks about the tape recorder she is using to record the interview. Interview topics include Odette's family, a relative who was killed during World War II, and how she met Milo. Dropout from 00:03:1100:03:23.
    Written on the cassette housing: Odette Min Rigaud - 3-11-82 / talk of nothing in particular - Milo - how long ago they were married (1934?) - the name of Mennesson. Who was shot by Germans, etc. Odette and translator friend / 3-11-82 - (2-6-10) talk with Odette Rigaud re Milo with translator friend. Married 46 years. Met in France. Milo lived there for 14-15 years. Married in Haiti. Tape length - Side I only? About 20 min.
  - Sound recording, February 27, 1984, AFC 2019/041: SR043; RYM 1072; 1 sound cassette (00:45:00): analog, 1 7/8 ips, half track, mono
    Content begins about 00:00:05. A man (probably Edward Berwet) can be heard singing bits of a song or songs. Traffic can be heard in the background, as well as recording equipment noise. There is a brief conversation, beginning about 00:02:07. A man can be heard in the background; possibly the recordist. The conversation begins at 00:03:53. Present during the interview: Leni Hamilton, Odette Rigaud, Shirley Keller, and Edward Berwet. The conversation alternates between French and English. In the recording Leni Hamilton says that Edward Berwet was recommended to her by Shirley Keller as a good source for stories relating to Vodou. Among other topics, Hamilton talks about the parallels between Greek mythology and Vodou. Toward the end of the recording it is made clear by Edward that Odette had been initiated as a mambo (priestess) but was not active in that role (she was not a practicing mambo).
    See SR054 for a partial dub of this tape.
    Written on the cassette label 1: Divine [?] / [other words]
    Written on the cassette label 2: Odette - Haiti
    Written on the cassette j-card: Interview and talk between Leni Hamilton and Odette Rigaud (Mennesont [sic]) and Edward Berwet / 2-27-84 4:30 p.m. Port-au-Prince Haiti
  - Sound recording, February 27, 1984 (Side A and part of Side B); July 26, 1977 (Side B), AFC 2019/041: SR054; RYR 3926; 1 sound cassette (Side A: 00:30:32, Side B: 00:16:10): analog, 1 7/8 ips, half track, stereo
    Side A: This is a copy of SR043, but lacking the first 00:04:19 of that recording.
    Side B: The content begins at 00:00:05. The dub of SR043 continues until about 00:04:43, and is immediately followed by a dub of the audio from the television show "In Search Of..."; specifically the episode on Vodou. Episodes in the series were narrated by Leonard Nimoy. This is episode 22 from Season 1. Rada and Petro (later Petwo) rites are referenced, and toward the end of the episode Maya Deren is quoted from her book The Divine Horsemen on the nature and purpose of possession. A very brief clip from a commercial is at the end of the recording.
    See SR043 for a more complete copy of the interview.
    Written on the cassette housing: Leni Hamilton / Rigaud / Voodoo [sic] - Haiti Port Au Prince / Leni Hamilton - Interview with Odette Rigaud and Edward B / Haiti - Feb. 1984 / Batteries ran down / Interview-continued. / TV Broadcast on Voodoo [sic] - March 1984
  - Sound recording, February 1984, AFC 2019/041: SR053; RYR 3925; 1 sound cassette (Side A: 00:45:00, Side B: 00:32:00): analog, 1 7/8 ips, half track, stereo; The cassette was reshelled before digitization.; There are frequent interruptions from phone calls, and background noise from a rooster crowing, from passing traffic, and people briefly interrupting the interview in person to ask Beauvoir questions.
    Side A: Leni Hamilton interviews Max Beauvoir. Hamilton gives some background about Greek ritual and its evolution into drama, and the same evolution in Ancient Egypt and Christian ritual during the Middle Ages [no country specified] and asks Beauvoir about the evolution of ritual to drama, and the myths about the lwa, and also how ancestors were transformed to lwa. Beauvoir's response is an overview of Vodou belief in regard to lwa, and also addresses the role of Christianity in beliefs, the mythological pantheon, the dead in Vodou belief as opposed to Christian belief, the materialization of spirits, and other topics. The conversation is multidisciplinary in nature (social, theological, etc.). Shirley Keller can also be heard occasionally on the recording.
    Side B: The conversation continues about 00:00:04, with an abrupt start (mid-sentence). He also recommends a movie about the guede (spirits of the dead) that Lila [Lilas] Desquiron (Director of Cultural Affairs, at Television Nationale), could get Hamilton access to view the video. Shirley Keller asks about vévé, and Milo Rigaud's book is mentioned, and Beauvoir praises it for its thoroughness on the treatment of vévés. He explains numerous terms and beliefs involved in Vodou, gives a reference to another published work. Keller suggests a Beauvoir apply for a grant or do work to publish a book on Vodou. Beauvoir says he doesn't have the time to write a book. He suggests that Hamilton could get a grant to write the book. Hamilton emphasizes the importance of documenting Vodou as a religion but cannot get a grant to study outside the U.S. Further topics include matriarchal cultures and the role of women in culture. Toward the end of the recording Keller takes photos of Beauvoir, and of Beauvoir and Hamilton together. Hamilton photographs Beauvoir and Keller together. The discussion moves to "voodoo [sic] dolls," when the recording ends abruptly.
    Written on the cassette housing: Leni Hamilton's interviews with Max Beauvoir - Voodoo [sic] Priest - Haiti - 2-84 / in Haiti
  - Sound recording, circa 1980s, AFC 2019/041: SR055; RYR 3927; 1 sound cassette (Side A: 00:45:00, Side B: 00:18:45): analog, 1.87 ips, half-track, stereo; The Peristyle de Mariani is Beauvoir's temple in Mariani, a suburb of Port-au-Prince. The interview is conducted in a house in Mariani. Traffic sounds in the background can be heard throughout the interview.
    Side A: The content begins about 00:00:12. Shirley Keller's interview with Max Beauvoir. He talks about the multiple roles of the houngan, and how he became the successor to his grandfather Brun Icart as a houngan. Other topics include misconceptions about Vodou, American marines in Haiti and the response to their presence, the role of the houngan, Vodou's role in Haitian identity, vévés and other elements of Vodou rites, locations where Vodou rites are conducted, how believers are possessed by lwa, the nature of fire, the experience of a person who has been possessed, the recognition of the presence of spirits, Vodou practices passed on as oral tradition, and voodoo dolls vs. paquet congo. The recording ends abruptly.
    Side B: The interview continues, with discussion of the paquet congo. Further topics include Vodou as a tool, the subject of dolls again, biki (smaller version of paquet congo) that are used for good luck. Keller reviews the facts about Beauvoir as the houngan of his hounfour and related details. Further topics discussed include fire-eating, various ceremonies, the categories of lwa, the function of animal sacrifice, the individual natures of lwa, interest in publishing in book form what he knows and the difficulties involved, discussion of Milo Rigaud's writing and the issue of Rigaud's mingling of opinions with facts, and the vévé on Keller's banjo. Keller explains that she had interviewed Beauvoir two years ago, but her tapes and the recorder were stolen while she was on the plane. She encourages people to come visit Haiti, and ends her part of the recording by saying her name and that of "The Folk People" (her radio show).
    Box panel: La Peristyle - Voodoo [sic] - Max Beauvoir
    Written on the cassette housing: Max Beauvoir - La Peristyle - Voodoo [sic]
  - Video recording, February 27, 1995, AFC 2019/041: MV01; VAS 7704; 1 videocassette (hi8, 01:01:04): digital
    Angus Gillespie's lecture on Haitian Vodou, at a gathering of members of the Rutgers University French Club. Towards the end, Shirley Keller speaks to the group briefly.
    Box panel: Angus Gillespie and Shirley Keller - Haitian voodoo [sic] at Rutgers French Club (unedited) / TC
- Series 3: Various sound recordings
  - Sound recording, undated, AFC 2019/041: SR056; WIRE 01088; 1 sound wire reel: analog
    Box panel: 3'/4 Flute chinoise / 5' Flute chinoise / 8/2 Méd[?] chinoise / 11[?] Inde / 16 Inde danse / 20 Java Surrend / 23 1/2 Harass / 27 habre ja / 30 Sonragbati / 33 1/2 Kenbang / 37 Kereos [other details, not transcribed]
    Box lid: Oriental 40'